So we pick up where we actually are
on target. Hold on a second. We pick up, exactly. So today's
דף *daf* is מב *Mem Bet* 42. We pick up three lines
from the bottom on the עמוד *amud* before, מא *Mem Aleph* עמוד
ב *amud bet*, and the topic under discussion is the nature of
טומטום Tumtum *tumtum* and אנדרוגינוס Androgynos *androgynos*, fascinating discussions, actually
around gender identity issues. So yesterday we said that there were a
couple of possibilities within an אנדרוגינוס Androgynos *androgynos*. It could be a,
you could take a position that it is ספק זכר ספק נקבה
safek zachar safek nekeivah, *safek zachar safek nekeiva*, which seems to be
obviously a categorical position, right? It's not like one is one and
one is the other, but it seems to be like its very
nature puts it in some indeterminate space between the two, would seem
to be the way to understand that. Or the possibility that it
is a זכר zachar, *zachar* with a מום mum? *mum*, or the
possibility, right, because it has female genitalia, or the possibility that it
is a third gender as we pointed out. It's interesting of course
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not consider the possibility that it's
a female with a מום mum *mum* because the presence of male
genitalia for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and for most of
ancient society was very much defined the male; the female is defined
as absence of male genitalia. So anyway, so you have the possibility
of indeterminate or בריה birya, בפני עצמה *beriyah bifnei atzmah* or male
with a מום mum *mum*. Now we move on to looking at
the issue about טומטום Tumtum, *tumtum*. So let's take a look. וחכמים
אומרים vechachamim omrim, אינו בכור bechor. *Ve-Chachamim omrim eino bechor*, the חכמים
chachamim *Chachamim* say that it is definitely not a בכור bechor? *bechor*,
this אנדרוגינוס androgynus. *androgynos*, because it is a totally third type of
a gender. אמר רב חסדא Rav Chisda *Amar Rav Chisda*, מחלוקת באנדרוגינוס
*machlokes be-androgynos*, the whole debate is by an אנדרוגינוס androgynus, *androgynos*, אבל
aval, בטומטום *aval be-tumtum*, דברי הכל ספק safek. הוא *divrei hakol safek
hu*, וקדוש מספק misafek, *ve-kadosh misafek*. A טומטום Tumtum. *tumtum* is somebody,
is an animal or a person with covered up genitalia, and therefore
it's a doubt, and that's not just a doubt in law, that's
not a question of how do you categorize it, right? Because there
the, it's a doubt in fact, what are the genitalia underneath this,
you know, that are hidden, that are covered up? So therefore he
says it's impossible that anybody would consider this to be its own
type of a gender. Everybody must admit that this is just a
question of fact and it's a doubt, and therefore it has, it's
like a doubtful בכור bechor *bechor*, so you don't give it to
a כהן *Kohen*, and the ישראל *Yisrael* eats it with, when it
gets a מום mum *mum*. Okay, that is its
status. אמר ליה amar lei, רבא *Amar lei Rava*, so רבא *Rava*
said to him, אלא מעתה *ela mei-ata*, if that's true, בערכין יהא
נערך *be-erchin yehei ne'erach*. So then if somebody says the ערך erech
*erech*, right, if you say the ערך *erech* of an individual is
on me, the תורה Torah *Torah* gives a chart based on male
or female and age. So somebody who is a טומטום Tumtum *tumtum*
should give, should also, if you give, if you say the ערך
*erech* of a person who's a טומטום Tumtum? *tumtum*, you are obligating
yourself to, you should have to pay the value. Now there'd be
a difference for male or female, so maybe you would pay the
male value just to be safe, but fundamentally it's one or the
other, you just don't know which, right? אלמה תניא *almah tanya*, why
do we teach in a ברייתא Braisah *braita*, top of מב עמוד
א *Mem Bet amud aleph*, הזכר hazachar *ha-zachar*, it says this is
the ערך *erech* of the הזכר hazachar, *ha-zachar*, והיה ערכך הזכר *ve-hayah
erkecha ha-zachar*, ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס v'lo Tumtum v'Androgynos, *ve-lo tumtum ve-androgynos*, and
not a טומטום tumtum *tumtum* and אנדרוגינוס androgynus. *androgynos*, they're not in
the פרשה *parsha*, not at all. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
סמי מכאן טומטום Sami mikan Tumtum, *sami mikan tumtum*. Okay, cross out
טומטום tumtum *tumtum*. Those are often quoted together, but basically they don't
deserve to be; really it's really all about אנדרוגינוס androgynus. *androgynos*. תא
שמע Ta shma, *Ta shema*, let's try again. יכול לא lo, יהיה
בערך איש אבל יהיה בערך אשה *Yachol lo yehei be-erech ish aval
yehei be-erech ishah*? Maybe I would think that a טומטום tumtum *tumtum*
slash אנדרוגינוס androgynus
*androgynos*
would not, you would not give him the value of a man,
but you'd give it that of a woman, like at least the
lesser value, because in the תורה Torah *Torah*'s chart the woman's, the
woman's value is, is less for ערך *erech*. תלמוד לומר הזכר *Talmud
lomar ha-zachar*, it stresses הזכר *ha-zachar*, and then it says ואם נקבה
nekeivah
*ve-im nekeiva*, and if she's a נקבה nekeivah, *nekeiva*. ולא v'lo, *Velo*,
so again the extra phrase אם *im*, I guess, seems to be
the extra, hard to exactly understand what's extra, but anyway, אבל לא
lo. טומטום ואנדרוגינוס tumtum ve'androgynus *aval lo tumtum ve-androgynos*. So you see
an אנדרוגינוס androgynus *androgynos* is excluded as well, and if it's just
a ספק safek. *safek*, then just treat it as you would any
case of ספק safek *safek*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, סמי
מכאן טומטום sami mikan tumtum. *sami mikan tumtum*, cross out the phrase
טומטום tumtum *tumtum*. Now we are going to go through a couple
of proofs like this, and this is one of the few times,
right, normally the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not, I mean every now
and then it gets really, you know, into a corner and it
just and it says, "Okay, switch the gears." But here very easily,
and it's like a regular answer, just cross out טומטום tumtum *tumtum*,
cross out טומטום tumtum *tumtum*. Now on the one hand, you sort
of understand that, because sometimes certain things come as a, you know,
package, and you really don't mean it about the package, like you
know, there are things like that in הלכה halacha *halacha*, חרש שוטה
וקטן *cheresh shoteh ve-katan*. So maybe there's a particular הלכה halacha *halacha*
where it's not relevant to one of them, but you just say
the phrase חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shoteh ve-katan*. So טומטום ואנדרוגינוס tumtum
ve'androgynus, *tumtum ve-androgynos* are the, you know, unclear genders, so you say
them together, but really the הלכה halacha *halacha* you only mean it.
But it is troubling that again and again and again you say
טומטום tumtum, *tumtum* if הלכה halacha *halacha*-ly it's not true. And the
funny thing is, and תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* himself realizes this, that you
could say that it is a factual doubt, but nevertheless the תורה
Torah *Torah* could be saying that sometimes the fact that something is
in a state of being a fact, that there is a factual
doubt and it has to do with the way the body is,
right, it's not that, it's not like just somehow you said somebody
behind a curtain you happen not to know whether. it was male
or female, right, this is a person that actually you cannot yet
determine, you won't be able to determine until something happens, whether they're
male or female, that maybe the תורה Torah dictates you could again,
maybe you could, maybe they were afraid that it would be the
surgery would be dangerous or something. Okay, it's an actual, it's we
require some type of cutting and surgery in order to uncover it.
Okay, so it could be that the תורה Torah actually might say
that yes, in this type of a case, because of the doubt,
you have to give it the its הלכה halacha is different. But
that's not exactly conceptually the same as saying it's a different gender,
right? No, it is male or female, but somebody is male or
female, but it's impossible to determine at this stage is somebody who
might have different הלכות halachos in either a male or a female.
But the גמרא Gemara
understands that רב חסדא Rav Chisda is rejecting that possibility. He's not
only saying that factually it's either a male or female and we
don't know, but he's actually saying that there would be no different
הלכה halacha. for this person. That the הלכה halacha would always be
just like any other case where you just didn't know, and you
would apply הלכות halachos of doubt, and you would not have special
הלכות halachos for this person. And therefore we have to consistently cross
out the word טומטום tumtum in all of these cases.
Okay, so in and what happens if you do say this? You
pay nothing.
You pay nothing, even though in fact he's either male or female.
Well no, according to the way we have the מסקנא maskana where
we cross out the word
אנדרוגינוס androgynus טומטום, tumtum then you pay the higher, you pay the
male out of ספק. safek, Yeah, you're מחמיר machmir out of ספק.
safek. Okay, but the way תוספות Tosfos explains this is,
but
if you said אנדרוגינוס androgynous, you'd pay nothing.
And the reason for that would be
because he's not, well presumably because it's a בריה בפני עצמו birya
bifnei atzmo according to this ברייתא baraisa would assume that if that's
our only possibility, ספק safek, or בריה, birya. then the reason here
would be בריה. beriah.
And the תורה Torah doesn't deal with it. So why don't they
at
least pay the value of? No, the תורה Torah says male or
female and not the third gender. Okay, what?
Well, isn't it מום?
mum, In two months? All right. Okay, so anyway so now we
go but okay, the way תוספות Tosafot expresses this is, you know,
maybe it's just השתני, ishtani, maybe the תורה Torah just says a
different הלכה halacha for somebody who is a male or female but
looks so different. But the גמרא Gemara is now resisting that. The
גמרא Gemara understands that according to רב חסדא Rav Chisda who says
it's a ספק, safek, means that there would be no special הלכות
halachos for this person. We would just treat it as we would
treat any other ספק. safek. And therefore it's going to consistently be
crossing out the word טומטום. tumtum Okay, so let's take a look.
תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear. אם זכר אם נקבה, Im
zachar im nekeivah, so this is the פסוק posuk that says by
שלמים, Shelamim, if it's a זכר, zachar this is what you know,
whether, excuse me, whether it's a זכר zachar whether it's a נקבה
nekeiva, you can bring it as a שלמים. Shelamim. Okay, ולא, or
of course you see what's coming, זכר ודאי נקבה ודאי, zachar vadai
nekeivah vadai, it has to be definitely a male or definitely a
female, ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, tumtum ve'androgynus, and those you cannot bring as
שלמים, Shelamim, even though you could bring either a זכר zachar or
a נקבה, nekeiva, you can't bring a זכר zachar שלמים. Shelamim. Now
that's a good proof that it's not a ספק, safek. right? Because
if it really were ספק, safek. well then the הלכה halakhic where
it doesn't matter male or female, you should be able to bring
a טומטום tumtum since it's only a ספק. safek. So the גמרא
Gemara, says סמי מכאן טומטום, tumtum okay, cross it off, doesn't belong
there.
You can't bring a טומטום?
tumtum. You can according to this as a שלמים. Shelamim. And how
would you say that it's not like it's a מום mum, or
something? All right, so you know, maybe even if that's true, it
might be different if it's a מום mum than, first of all
we had a debate, maybe we don't consider these things a מום
mum, in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, and it certainly would not be
as categorically excluded. Maybe it would be like being מקדיש makdish a
זכר zachar with a מום, mum. but it wouldn't be like it's
completely irrelevant, right? It wouldn't be like being מקדיש makdish a, you
know, like I don't know, a horse for?
No, but it's a
מום קבוע, mum kavua, right?
Maybe, maybe, but it's still I understand, but first of all, not
necessarily, not necessarily, we had a debate in the משנה Mishnah whether
it was a מום, mum, right, maybe it's something that could heal
and so on, there are cases where it gets uncovered, number one.
And number two, as a there's a difference between being מקדיש makdish
something with a מום mum, and being מקדיש makdish something that is
categorically excluded. Okay, so anyway the גמרא Gemara here is saying yes.
Now the real question is of course that the דרשה derasha is
as I said before, זכר ודאי נקבה ודאי. zachar vadai nekeivah vadai.
So I could admit that this is one or the other but
I could still say the תורה Torah demands that I know which
one, that I have a clear identity at the time of being
מקדיש. makdish. So that is the גמרא Gemara treats רב חסדא's Rav
Chisda position as an as a very extreme position. Not just it's
a factual doubt, but it's a factual doubt and therefore the תורה
would never treat it differently than if it than any other case
of ספק. safek Okay, and therefore refuses to accept that it would
have a different הלכה. So therefore it says you're right, according to
רב חסדא Rav Chisda you could bring it as a שלמים. Shelamim.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, הנרבע והמוקצה, Haneerva v'hamuktzeh,
so an animal this is what this is what we ואתנן ומחיר
וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס, v'esnan u'mechir v'Tumtum v'Androgynos,
so all of these are now we're talking about bird sacrifices. So
you remember by a bird you do מליקה, melikah, right from the
back of the neck. If it weren't a sacrifice then that would
make it a נבילה. neveilah. Now one of the signs of a
נבילה neveilah is that when you swallow it you become טמא. tamei.
So for some reason that's the one we're going to focus on
right now and we want to say if you bring a bird
קרבן korban which is completely פסול pasul as a קרבן, korban, then
the act of מליקה melikah is not a כשר kosher act of
שחיטה, shechitah, it makes it a נבילה, neveilah, when you eat it
you're טמא. tamei. So הנרבע, Haneerva, so whether it was a bird
that was worshipped והמוקצה v'hamuktzeh or set aside for עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, ואתנן ומחיר v'esnan u'mechir or whether it was given as payment
for a prostitute or whether it was exchanged for a dog, those
are the categories of exclusion, the טומטום ואנדרוגינוס tumtum ve'androgynous, or a
bird that's a טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. androgynous Now what is powerful
about this statement is that while by שלמים shlamim the תורה says
whether male or female, the תורה never mentions gender at all by
birds. Right, it's one thing to say it could be either A
or B. Well, what if it's C? Okay, C is different. Right,
what if it's somewhere between A or B? I don't know, okay,
that's neither clearly A or B. That's the שלמים shlamim case. But
a bird doesn't even mention gender, right? So there you would think,
so there's no looking at the issues of gender altogether. And nevertheless
we say, no, if it's טומטום tumtum or אנדרוגינוס, androgynous that therefore
it is going to be a, that it is going to be
a, where am I? טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, tumtum ve'androgynous. כולם מטמאים בגדים בבית
הבליעה. kulam metamei begadim beveit hablia. They all make you טמא tamei
and your clothes טמא tamei when you swallow them. It's a נבלה
neveila because it's not a כשר kosher bird sacrifice. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, טומטום ואנדרוגינוס אין מטמאים
בגדים בבית הבליעה. tumtum ve'androgynus ein metamei begadim beveit hablia. No, it's
not true by birds. And as תוספות says, he's not just saying
it's not a נבלה, neveila, he would actually say it's a כשר
kosher קרבן. korban. Why? שהיה רבי אליעזר אומר, shehaya Rabbi Eliezer omer,
כל מקום שנאמר זכר ונקבה, kol makom shene'emar zachar unekeiva, אתה מוציא
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. ata motzi tumtum ve'androgynus.
If it says male or female, even by שלמים shlamim where it
says both זכר zachar and נקבה, nekeiva, fine, then you exclude טומטום
tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. androgynous. They're neither male nor female, clearly you exclude
them. Okay, there it's a
gender, it matters. אבל, but by birds, הואיל ולא נאמר בו זכר
ונקבה, ho'il velo ne'emar bo zachar unekeiva, it doesn't say male or
female at all. It doesn't mention gender. אין אתה מוציא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס
מביניהם. ein ata motzi tumtum ve'androgynus mibeinehen. You do not exclude טומטום
tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. androgynous A very reasonable argument. Okay, so he says
they're completely included. Anyway, what you see is that according to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, טומטום tumtum is excluded. Why should טומטום tumtum
be excluded if it doesn't even say, you know, if it's either
זכר zachar or נקבה, nekeiva same like the question by שלמים? shlamim?
And again the גמרא's Gemara answer is, צמי מכאן טומטום. tzami mikan
tumtum. Exclude טומטום, tumtum, cross it out. Now again, as Michael said,
he's right, you know, especially when you're dealing with קרבנות, korbanot, it's
one thing by ערך where you would say it's either one or
the other and then you maybe have to go crossing it out.
But by קרבנות, korbanot, if you're excluding things like, I don't know,
you know, נבלה neveila and מוקצה muktzeh and so on, you could
exclude these things not because they don't qualify as male or female,
but because they're different. And that difference is enough to exclude them.
Call it a מום, mum, call it a separate פסול, psul, but
it doesn't have to be because you're saying that because of their
gender is per se, you know, they're not male, not female, it's
just because of this physical reality they're excluded. Anyway, that is, I
agree, you could have definitely said that. The גמרא Gemara really takes
רב חסדא Rav Chisda to an extreme and assumes according to him,
you know, a very inclusivist position. So טומטום tumtum is never going
to be treated differently than if it was just a clear case
of any other thing that was a ספק. safek. Do you want
to say something, Charlie? You're looking up the frequency of... oh, I
thought you were looking up the frequency of androgyny in birds, right?
Well, that's the thing, I'm trying to find out how easy it
is to...
oh, that might be true. I certainly know that by some, by
some ducks and whatever, because this came up earlier in the גמרא,
Gemara I forget under what the context was, but right, but that
the, that the whole genitalia is hidden and it only comes out
like at the time of mating or something.
Yeah, you can tell, you can tell the mallard duck, which is
the ancestor of all ducks, the colors of the feathers are noticeably
different, but the genitalia are not.
And there's a parrot that was sold to them as a male
and it laid eggs that started
to lay.
So now you understand why, right, why it doesn't even mention it.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, הטרפה והכלאים ויוצא דופן
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס לא קדושים ולא מקדישים. hatreifa vehakilayim veyotzei dofen tumtum ve'androgynus
lo kedoshim velo maktishim.
Now here, by the way, Michael, you see an example of how
it's more than a בעל מום. ba'al mum. These are more categorically
excluded. So here is by a הלכה about תמורה, tmura,
and
you try to either transfer קדושה kedusha from a קרבן korban onto
them, which by the way works, you're not allowed to, of course,
every תמורה tmura is אסור, assur, you're violating a לאו, lav, but
when you try to do it, the animal becomes, second animal becomes
קדוש kadosh as well, even if it has a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, even if it's a blemish. But not if it's more categorically
excluded. And here why it matters that טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgonus
or whatever are not just an issue of מום. mum, Okay, so
the statement is, if it's a טומטום tumtum. and אנדרוגינוס androgonus and
the other things in the list which we'll go back to, and
you try to do תמורה tmura and transfer from one thing from
A to B, and B is טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, tumtum ve'androgynous it doesn't
become קדוש kadosh at all. If it was just a בעל מום,
ba'al mum, it would become קדוש, kadosh, but if it's טומטום tumtum.
or אנדרוגינוס androgonus, and it's categorically excluded, it does not. That's לא
קדושים. lo kedoshim. And what's לא מקדישים? lo maktishim? If it was
קדוש, kadosh, now how did it become קדוש? kadosh? I thought you
said that it couldn't even become קדוש. kadosh. Because maybe it was
born to another, its mother was a קרבן. korban. Its mother was
a שלמים shlamim and it was born. So that allows it to
become קדוש kadosh even things that are more categorically excluded. So if
somehow it was קדוש kadosh as being born to an animal that
was a קרבן, korban, it can now not transfer the קדושה kedusha
from that to something else. So the basic point is the things
on these lists are categorically excluded, are not just מומים, mumim, and
therefore cannot become קדוש kadosh even in a case of תמורה. tmura.
And of course on this list... is going to be טומטום tumtum
and אנדרוגינוס, androgonus which is going to be a problem yet again.
Michael, what did you want to say?
Just so I understand, when you say לא מקדישים lo makdishim means
what?
If they were born from, they had קדושה kedusha in the case
where their mother was a קרבן korban and they were born to
their, so they were born from an animal that was a קרבן.
korban. That allows them to have קדושה kedusha even though they're in
this categorical exclusion category. Nevertheless, if you try to do תמורה temurah
from them to something else, the other thing would not become תמורה.
temurah.
So that's לא מקדישים? lo makdishim? לא מקדישים. lo makdishim. And then
לא קדוש lo kadosh means
if you take an animal that is a קרבן korban and you
try to transfer to them, they do not become. Even though תמורה
temurah works on a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Okay, so let's take
a look. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, הטרפה והכלאים, hatreifah vehakilayim,
so טרפה treifah we know, כלאים kilayim is a
crossbreed, even presumably of two kosher, of two like a sheep and
a goat, two things that would be themselves כשר קרבנות. kasher korbanot.
ויוצא דופן, veyotzei dofen, a
Caesarean section. טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, tumtum v'androgonus לא קדושים, lo kedoshim, do not
become קדוש kadosh when you try to transfer תמורה temurah onto them.
ולא מקדישים, velo makdishim, or they do not make other things
קדוש. kadosh. ואמר שמואל, ve'amar Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel clarifies, לא קדושים
בתמורה ולא מקדישים לעשות תמורה. lo kedoshim betemurah velo makdishim la'asot temurah.
Like I just said, they do not become קדוש kadosh in תמורה,
temurah, they don't make other things. And here again it points to
the point that it's obviously more, much more of a categorical exclusion
than just a blemish. And you see we mentioned טומטום. tumtum, So
you see טומטום tumtum. is clearly being treated as a separate category
and is categorically excluded and is not just a ספק. safek Even
a ספק safek, with a blemish it's not. It's much more categorically
excluded than just a ספק. safek. So the גמרא Gemara again says,
סמי מכאן טומטום. tumtum. Fine, erase טומטום tumtum from here. It doesn't
belong in this list. Now, one of the reasons that the גמרא
Gemara might be assuming that רב חסדא Rav Chisda meant his position
to an extreme is because רב חסדא Rav Chisda did not just
say it as an abstract. רב חסדא Rav Chisda said it in
explaining our משנה, mishnah, which is talking about a בכור. bechor, So
if רב חסדא Rav Chisda. was prepared to admit, look, some of
it, it's a ספק safek some of the time, but when it
comes to קרבנות, korbanot, there I admit it's categorically excluded. Okay, then
why are you saying they don't debate by בכור? bechor, Our משנה
mishnah is about בכור bechor, and then it should be the same
point that it should be categorically excluded. So since he's saying it
by our משנה, mishnah, which is about בכור, bechor, it seems to
be saying that even in an extreme case of קרבנות korbanot that
has a lot of categories of invalidity, טומטום tumtum is not among
a category of פסול. psul. טומטום tumtum is just a ספק, safek,
nothing more than your standard ספק. safek Okay, and that's what it
is. Like the same way you had a ספק safek, if the
animal had given birth before and was it a בכור, bechor. טומטום
tumtum is ספק זכר ספק נקבה, safek zachar safek nekeva. no separate
category of פסול, psul, even by a בכור, bechor. even by קרבנות.
korbanot. Okay, so that's why we have to do a lot of
crossing out according to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda תא שמע, come and
hear.
Now
it's going to be hard to cross out because now we're going
to have a number. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, חמישה, chamishah,
there are five animals, לא קדושים ולא מקדישים. lo kedoshim velo makdishim.
They cannot become קדוש kadosh by תמורה temurah and can't be מקדיש
makdish by תמורה. temurah. ואלו הן, ve'eilu hein, and these are they:
הטרפה והכלאים, hatreifah vehakilayim, right, טרפה, treifah, crossbreed, יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen,
C-section, טומטום tumtum ואנדרוגינוס.
There you go. Five! And טומטום tumtum is one of them. So
how can you cross out? וכי תימא הכי נמי סמי מכאן טומטום,
vechi teima hachi nami sami mikan tumtum,
unless you want to say cross out טומטום, tumtum הוו להו ארבעה,
havu lehu arba'ah, it's only four. So the גמרא Gemara of course
has an answer. The גמרא Gemara says, you could say cross out
four or five, it's like four. But then it doesn't say it,
it says, אפיק
טומטום ועייל יתום. afik tumtum ve'ayeil yatom. Okay, take out טומטום tumtum
and replace it with the word יתום, yatom, an orphan. What's an
יתום? yatom? When the animal is born and the mother dies. Because
we actually say the פסוק pasuk says שבעת ימים יהיה תחת אמו
ומיום השמיני והלאה, shivat yamim yihyeh tachat imo umiyom hashemini vahalah, which
doesn't only mean that it's only כשר kasher as a קרבן korban
by day eight, but means that if its mother was not alive
when it was born and for the first seven days, it actually
can never be a קרבן. korban. Okay, so therefore we are once
again changing the גרסא. girsa. טומטום tumtum ואנדרוגינוס really it doesn't mean
it, it really means אנדרוגינוס androgonus and the five is a missing
one. So a lot of
editing. What? יוצא דופן. yotzei dofen. C-section, Caesarean section. Okay. So alright,
so anyway, so again it's a lot of editing. Clearly the sense
of a lot of these ברייתות braitot is even if you say
it's a ספק, safek. it might be a ספק safek that because
of its physical nature of its ספק, safek it gets excluded especially
from the world of קרבנות. korbanot. But that is not רב חסדא's
Rav Chisda position. He treats it no more than a ספק. safek,
לימא כתנאי, leima kitannai, let's say maybe this is based on a
debate of תנאים. tannaim. רבי אלעאי אומר, Rabbi Ilai omer, here's another
רבי אלעאי, Rabbi Ilai, משום רבי ישמעאל, mishum Rabbi Yishmael, in the
name of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, אנדרוגינוס בכור הוא ומומו עמו. androgynous
bechor hu umumo imo. This is like the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
of our משנה. mishnah. Here it's רבי אלעאי Rabbi Ilai in his
name. An אנדרוגינוס androgonus, is a בכור, bechor, it's a definite male
with a blemish. Or we discussed yesterday whether it was ספק safek,
male, ספק safek female, and even if it's a male it has
a blemish. But anyway, certainly you say even if it's a male
or it's a definite male and it has a מום, mum, and
therefore you can שחט shacht it and eat it, but you cannot
work it. It's a male with a blemish. That's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael by אנדרוגינוס. androgonus. וחכמים אומרים, and the sages say, and this
was the sages of our משנה, mishnah, אין קדושה חלה עליו. ein
kedusha chalah alav. No, an אנדרוגינוס androgonus. is a third gender and
it's definitely not male, and therefore it is no קדושה kedusha at
all, you can work it and so on. Okay, that is like
the sages of our משנה. mishnah. Now we have a third position
not mentioned in our משנה. mishnah. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon. Now Rabbi
Shimon ben Yehuda in the name of Rabbi Shimon, הרי הוא אומר,
harei hu omer, the verse says
הזכר that by בכור. bechor. It says what's the פסוק? pasuk? הזכר
תקדיש. hazachar takdish. Okay, so it says the male. וכל מקום שנאמר
זכר אינו אלא להוציא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. v'chol makom shene'emar zachar eino ela
l'hotzi tumtum v'androgonus.
And therefore טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgonus, are being categorically excluded. Now
how is that different? Just a second ago, right, we heard that
the חכמים chachamim? say that אנדרוגינוס androgynous. is categorically excluded. So what
did he add to the חכמים? He's also saying it's categorically excluded.
He added one word. What word did he add? Anybody pay attention?
טומטום. tumtum, He said, until now we've been talking about אנדרוגינוס, androgynous,
right? The question is, is אנדרוגינוס androgynous. a male with a blemish?
Is אנדרוגינוס androgynous categorically excluded? And he says הזכר, טומטום tumtum ואנדרוגינוס
are categorically excluded. So the only thing he's adding is the word
טומטום. tumtum So therefore it seems like they're debating whether טומטום tumtum.
is a separate gender and categorically excluded or not. So let's take
a look. We
also, you know, besides a פסוק. pasuk. וכי תימא סמי מכאן טומטום
v'chi teima sarmi mikan tumtum and
unless you want to say cross out the word טומטום, tumtum רבי
שמעון יהודה היינו רבנן, Rabbi Shimon Yehuda hainu rabbanan, then he's saying
the exact same as the rabbis. The only thing he added was
the word טומטום. tumtum אלא לאו טומטום איכא בינייהו, ela lav tumtum
ika beineihu, it seems that they're debating whether to fully exclude טומטום.
tumtum דתנא קמא סבר אין קדושה חלה עליו אנדרוגינוס, d'tanna kama savar
ein kedusha chalah alav androgonus,
that when do we say there's no קדושה kedusha at all, it's
its own gender, that's an אנדרוגינוס, androgynous and therefore it's not at
all male and it's not in בכור. bechor. That's what they say
about אנדרוגינוס. androgynous אבל טומטום ספקא הוא וקדוש מספקא, aval tumtum safeika
hu v'kadosh misafeika, but they would say a טומטום tumtum. I admit
is a doubt because every case is different, we just don't know,
right? Because you understand why טומטום tumtum is so different, right? Because
every animal that's a טומטום tumtum? might have male genitalia, might have
female. Each animal is different. So that's just a doubt, that's not
a different category, and therefore it's קדוש מספק. kadosh misafek. That's תנא
קמא, tanna kama, only talking about אנדרוגינוס. androgynous, ואתא רבי שמעון בן
יהודה למימר, v'ata Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda l'meimar, and then comes Rabbi
Shimon ben Yehuda to say, טומטום בריה הוא. tumtum birya hu. No,
טומטום tumtum is just like an אנדרוגינוס, androgynous. it's its own category,
at least until the genitalia are exposed. ולא קדוש, v'lo kadosh, and
it is not holy at all, it is completely a separate category.
That seems to be the simple debate. So your question whether we
look at טומטום tumtum as a separate category or not, you're insisting
it's not a separate category, not even for קרבנות. korbanot. At least
here we have רבי שמעון יהודה Rabbi Shimon Yehuda that says at
least for קרבנות korbanot it has a totally separate category, it's categorically
excluded. That seems to be the debate. So the גמרא Gemara of
course resists this. And the גמרא Gemara says לא, no, that's not
necessarily what they're debating. דכולי עלמא טומטום בבריה לא מספקא. d'chulei alma
tumtum b'birya lo mesafkeih.
Nobody is arguing that a טומטום tumtum is its own category and
is categorically excluded. זכר ונקבה הוא
דמספקא. zachar u'nekeiva hu d'mesafkeih. The question is, now it gets interesting,
we're going to say follow רב חסדא's Rav Chisda, line of reasoning
that a טומטום tumtum. is either a זכר zachar, or a נקבה,
nekeiva. it's just a doubt and each one is different. So if
each one is different, maybe there's ways we can determine before the
genitalia are exposed. What would be those ways? So by animals, if
it is a זכר, zachar then where it urinates from is very
different than if it's a נקבה nekeiva where it urinates from. So
even though it's exposed, it's covered up, presumably somehow there's some hole
and space where the urine can still exit from, even though it's
all covered up by like a layer of skin. So let's just
see where the urine comes from and determine whether this animal is
a זכר zachar, or a נקבה. nekeiva. And that's the question, whether
we can, everybody agrees it's a ספק, safek. follow רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda no special הלכה for this, and now it's just a question
of determining fact. So let's inspect it and see if we can
determine it. So let's take a look. זכר נקבה הוא דמספקא, zachar
nekeiva hu d'mesafkeih, we're trying to figure out if it's male or
female in every particular location. מטיל מים
במקום זכרות, matil mayim b'makom zachrut, if the urine comes out in
the place where the male genitalia would normally be then and normally
would exit if it were a male, then דכולי עלמא לא פליגי
דזכר הוא, d'chulei alma lo pligi d'zachar hu, everybody would agree that
it's a male. There's no way if it were a נקבה nekeivah,
the urine would be able to come out from that location. כי
פליגי במטיל מים במקום נקבות. ki pligi b'matil mayim b'makom nekeivut. They
argue when the water comes out, the urine comes out from where
it would come out if it were a נקבה. nekeivah, מר סבר
חיישינן שמא נהפכה זכרותו לנקבותו, mar savar chashinan shema nehepcha zachruto l'nechvuto,
since the whole thing is covered up, you don't know where the
male genitalia is, right? And the male genitalia can, you know, can
move around, I mean not move from where it's attached to the
body, but the male organ can be in different locations. So maybe
if it's covered up, maybe the male organ is folded over and
it's pointing towards the rear of the animal, and maybe the urine
is coming out from the back because it is a זכר, zachar
but it's a זכר zachar with the male organ that is in
a different location, again not different location where it's attached to the
body, but where it actually is where the opening is pointing. That's
what
one holds. ומר סבר לא חיישינן, u'mar savar lo chashinan, we're not
concerned. And therefore what are they debating? So you're right, the second
opinion says it is definitely excluded, but not definitely excluded because it
is categorically its own category. We're talking about the particular case of
a טומטום tumtum that is urinating from where... We're talking about the
particular case of a טומטום tumtum that is urinating from where it
would come out from a female. And therefore, the second opinion says,
"Ah, that's completely excluded. I, that's definitely a female, no problem, not
a בכור," bechor. for talking about בכור. bechor. So females are excluded.
And the earlier opinion says, "No, I'm only excluding an אנדרוגינוס. androgynous
This case, at least, is a ספק זכר." safek zachar. And that's
not to say it's a definite male, but it might be a
male. I can't determine based on where it's urinating from that it's
not a male. That's not sufficient evidence. So yes, they're debating whether
טומטום tumtum is ספק זכר safek zachar or לא זכר lo zachar
at all, but not because as a category it's excluded, but because
we're dealing with particular cases where it's urinating from the place where
it would normally come out if it were a female. And is
that enough evidence or not? Okay, so that's how we're framing the
debate. And now we're going to have an actual practical case. Let's
take a look. כי
הא, ki ha, like the case דהורה רבי אילא—some dehorei Rabbi Ila
have the גרסא girsa Rabbi Ila, some have רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar.
If it's Rabbi Ila, then it's a different Rabbi Ila because this
is an אמורא, Amora, as we'll see. בהמה המטיל מים במקום נקבה.
beheimah hamatil mayim bimkom nekeivah.
So there was an animal that actually was urinating where normally it
would come out if it were a female, toward at the rear
of the animal. Okay, and this was again, this was obviously a
טומטום, tumtum and there was a question about a בכור. bechor. And
he said, "חולין, chullin, it's complete חולין, chullin, לא ספק lo safek
at all. It's a definite נקבה, nekeivah? not a problem." So again,
based on the assumption not that as a category טומטום tumtum is
excluded, but by identifying this particular animal, we can identify that it
was a female based on how it urinated. So תמה רבי יוחנן.
tamah Rabbi Yochanan. Rabbi Yochanan was astounded about this ruling. It takes
a lot of, you know, that takes a lot of courage to
פסקן pasken that position. מאן לא חש לתנא קמא ולרבי ישמעאל? man
lo chash le-Tanna Kamma u-le-Rabbi Yishmael? So how could you not be
concerned with the opinions of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי
ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? What does that mean? If you remember our משנה
mishnah began by saying טומטום tumtum, and אנדרוגינוס, androgynous right? And it
said it's a ספק, safek? ספק safek whether זכר or נקבה, nekeivah
and therefore you don't שחט shacht it out of the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, you don't bring it as a קרבן. korban. And then
there were debates about אנדרוגינוס. androgynous Well, maybe an אנדרוגינוס Androgynus has
a מום, mum. maybe אנדרוגינוס androgynous is a separate בריה. beriah. But
nobody in the משנה mishnah disagreed about טומטום. tumtum Everybody in the
משנה mishnah accepted the first statement that טומטום tumtum was a ספק.
safek, So how can he rule that it's a definite נקבה? Okay,
and what would be the case now, based on what we've said,
that a טומטום tumtum is a ספק? safek. It can't be when
the urine comes out where it would as a male; that would
prove that it's ודאי זכר. vadai zachar. So the case of it
being a ספק safek. could only be the case where the urine
is coming out where it would as a female. So Rabbi Yochanan
is saying, "I don't get it. In our משנה, mishnah, everybody agrees
that טומטום tumtum is a ספק, safek. presumably it's the case where
it's coming out from where it would as a female. So how
do you have the חוצפה chutzpah to פסקן pasken that it's a
definite male—I mean, it's a definite female?" Okay, so how could you
ignore the משנה? mishnah? So the גמרא Gemara says, ולימא רבי יוחנן
נמי מאן דלא חש לרבנן בתראי? ve-leima Rabbi Yochanan nami man dela
chash le-Rabbanan basrai? Why did he only quote רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
and the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? How about the last רבנן? Rabbanan?
Remember the רבנן בתראי Rabbanan basrai said an אנדרוגינוס androgynous is a
separate בריה. They also didn't mention a טומטום. tumtum So they also
implicitly agree that a טומטום tumtum, is a ספק. safek, And how
do I know that they're implicitly agreeing about a טומטום? tumtum, דאמר
רב חסדא מחלוקת באנדרוגינוס, de-amar Rav Chisda machlokes be-androgynous, because רב חסדא
Rav Chisda, even clarified, he said, "This whole position that it's a
separate category is only by the אנדרוגינוס, androgynous אבל בטומטום דברי הכל
ספק, aval be-tumtum divrei hakol safek, that even the later rabbis agree
that it's a doubt." So according to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda everybody
in the משנה mishnah agreed that טומטום tumtum. was a doubt. The
only person who said otherwise was this ברייתא braita, we quoted before,
we quoted a few minutes ago, that said, "No, if it comes
from the female place, then it's a female." But in the משנה,
mishnah, everybody agreed to the original statement that a טומטום tumtum. was
a doubt. So if Rabbi Yochanan was saying, "How dare you פסקן
pasken against the משנה?", mishnah? why didn't he say, "How dare you
פסקן pasken against all three תנאים Tannaim of the משנה?" mishnah? Is
this clear to everybody? Our משנה mishnah introduces טומטום ספק, tumtum safek,
אנדרוגינוס ספק. androgynous safek. And then there's two other opinions about אנדרוגינוס.
There's, you know, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says אנדרוגינוס has a
מום, mum. is a male with a מום, and then the last
רבנן Rabbanan that say an אנדרוגינוס is a separate category. But implicitly—and
this is what רב חסדא Rav Chisda. opened by saying—everybody agrees that
טומטום tumtum, is a ספק. safek. Nobody disagrees about טומטום. tumtum So
you've got everybody in the משנה mishnah saying טומטום tumtum, is a
ספק. safek How dare you פסקן pasken that טומטום tumtum is a
נקבה if the urine comes out from that place? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. So Rabbi Yochanan לא סבירא ליה דרב
חסדא. lo sevira lei de-Rav Chisda. He doesn't agree with רב חסדא.
He thinks—because remember we had all those משניות mishnayos a minute ago—so
he thinks that the rabbis at the end of the משנה mishnah
that say that an אנדרוגינוס is its own category would also say
a טומטום tumtum, is its own category. I mean, thank God, right?
Because you really didn't want to go to bed thinking that we
completely changed the גרסא girsa of all these משניות mishnayos and there
wasn't an alternative. So now we are finding out that, yes, Rabbi
Yochanan does say—now what does that mean? is an interesting question. Does
it mean for all הלכות halachos it's its own category? Meaning there
is the physical reality it's one or the other. Or maybe it
means for a range of הלכות, halachos, like particularly קרבנות, korbanos, since
it's indeterminate now, that gives it different הלכות. halachos. We're not really
saying
it's a third gender, but we're saying since we can't determine the
gender right now, it's not included in the world of קרבנות. korbanos.
Either way. At least רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* is admitting
that at least for all of these משניות *mishnayot* and for, you
know, our משנה Mishna *mishna*, the same approach that says אנדרוגינוס *Androginos*
is its own category would also say that טומטום tumtum *Tumtum* is
its own category. So he says like this, he says look, I
understand that you have the last opinion in the משנה Mishnah, *mishna*
to back you. I don't say like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. I'm
willing to admit that the last opinion in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*
that says אנדרוגינוס *Androginos* is its own category would also say the
same by טומטום tumtum *Tumtum*, at least let's say for the world
of קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*. Fine, but still you're going against the first
two opinions of the משנה *mishna*. Okay, so how do you ignore
the first two opinions of the משנה *mishna* and just פסקן pasken
*pasken* blithely like the third one? According to the first two, טומטום
tumtum *Tumtum* is a ספק safek *safek*. Let's just see the answer.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so that's why he didn't say
all three positions because he disagrees with רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says אי לא סבירא ליה לימא הוא דאמר
כרבנן בתראי *Ee lo sevira lei leima hu de'amar kerabbanan basrai*. So
then what's bothering him? Why couldn't he just say that this פסק
*psak* of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer* or רב אלעזר *Rav
Elazar* was going like the last opinion in the משנה *mishna*? That's
not so crazy. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says אי לא סבירא
ליה *Ee lo sevira lei*, I'm sorry, I just said לימא הוא
דאמר כרבנן בתראי *leima hu de'amar kerabbanan basrai*. No, הכי נמי קאמר
*Hachi nami ka'amar*. You're right, that's what he's saying. מן שבק תרי
ועביד כחד *Man shavak terei ve'avid kachad*? Who has the חוצפה *chutzpah*
to leave the first to abandon the two positions in the משנה
*mishna* and just, you know, פסקן pasken *pasken* like the third? What's
your evidence that we פסקן pasken *pasken* like the third position that
you can מתיר *matir* a בכור *bechor*? Okay, so now what we
have is a very impressive debate about טומטום tumtum *Tumtum*, right? Because
again, we have the רבנן בתראי Rabbanan Basrai *Rabbanan Basrai* of the
משנה *mishna* that say אנדרוגינוס *Androginos* is a third gender. What's the
story with טומטום tumtum *Tumtum*? So רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says a
very reasonable thing, which is טומטום tumtum *Tumtum* every case is different.
It's just a ספק safek *safek*. Okay, but we have all of
these ברייתות *braitot* and משניות *mishnayot* that basically say that טומטום tumtum
*Tumtum* is categorically excluded. So comes along רבי, so he crosses it
out. Comes along רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says
you're right. The same opinion that says, I disagree with רב חסדא
*Rav Chisda*, the same opinion that says that אנדרוגינוס *Androginos* is its
own category says טומטום tumtum, *Tumtum* is its own category. And therefore
it's excluded from all these world of קרבנות *korbanot*. Now within that
תוספות *Tosafot* explores this. It's possible to subdivide that into two conceptual
categories. One is that it's really a third gender, which is a
little strange because it is one or the other just covered up.
Or what seems to be more, you know, the possibility, which is
I admit that it's one or the other, but an animal that's
one or the other that is, that you cannot, it's impossible at
this stage to determine it based on its physical biological, you know,
nature, that has to have different הלכות *halachot* that apply to it
and that could be more categorically excluded. So it's like a separate
category in הלכה *halacha* but not really saying it's a separate gender.
Okay, but anyway that is what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, which
keeps the simple sense of all those משניות *mishnayot*. Now if you
say it's a real ספק safek *safek*, then you want to say
can we look at evidence to determine one or the other? And
that's the question of where it urinates from. So then there's the
possibility that it was urinating from where female would urinate from, we
can definitely determine its female. That was one position in a ברייתא
braita. *braita* and that was the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer*. But רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* was offended that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* could take that position and not be concerned
about those that say it's a separate category or those that say
that even when it urinates from that place, from the rear, that
it still is a ספק safek? *safek*. Okay, so is that clear
again? What is a
טומטום tumtum *Tumtum*? אנדרוגינוס *Androginos* is either by definition a ספק safek.
*safek* or it's a male with a מום *mum* or it's a
third gender. A טומטום tumtum *Tumtum* is either a ספק safek, *safek*.
If it's a ספק safek *safek*, then your question is going, each
case is different. Can we determine what it is by where it
urinates from? If it urinates from where a female would urinate from,
some say that we can determine. Some say no, maybe it's just
the male male organ turned in the wrong way. So that's one
question. Or is it actually categorically excluded, either because it's its own
gender or even if it's not its own gender, it's just categorically
excluded? So those are the range of positions. But in our משנה
*mishna*, the emphasis is that a טומטום tumtum *Tumtum* is a ספק
safek. *safek*. It's here, it's a ספק *safek* and you can't determine.
So רבי, so therefore רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* was offended. How do
you go ahead and פסקן pasken *pasken* that it's in the category
of ספק *safek* and that also you can actually determine that it
is a female, or that it is categorically excluded when our משנה
*mishna* takes the position that it's a ספק *safek*?
So apparently, I
would imagine this would have been said here, there's no clear ruling,
משנה *mishna*, ברייתא braita. *braita*, anywhere that like really says טומטום *Tumtum*
and not אנדרוגינוס *Androginos* like that, you know, that טומטום *Tumtum* is
good. No, yeah, whatever it is. No, just says like, you know,
this
הלכה *halacha* is just by אנדרוגינוס *Androginos* and
not by טומטום *Tumtum* one way or the other.
I think you're correct, not that I know of. Okay, so anyway,
I hope you have this all clear because there's going to be
a quiz at the end. Okay, so now, did you want to
say something, Charlie?
Because I'm saying the משנה *mishna* is not completely clear.
Well, the משנה *mishna* starts with both and ends with just אנדרוגינוס
*Androginos*, which is why רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says that טומטום *Tumtum*
is agreed that it's a ספק *safek*. Okay, what's our question?
Yeah, well the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say that in a
minute. But again, the possibility to exclude טומטום *Tumtum* now is two
possibilities. One is you could either say why is טומטום *Tumtum* excluded
from בכור *bechor* if it's completely not a בכור *bechor* like רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי אליעזר געזונטהייט, gesundheit, there's now two conceptual ways
to say it's completely not a בכור. One is you take the
position like רבנן Rabbanan בתראי and you assume it applies to טומטום
as well. אנדרוגינוס is a separate category, טומטום is a separate category,
categorically excluded, therefore not a בכור. Or you could say I admit
it's a ספק, but if it's urinating from the place from the
rear where a female urinates from, then I also know that it's
a female. So there's two ways to get to excluding a טומטום,
either by categorical exclusion or by trying to identify it as a
female. Okay, and now let's take a look at that exact point
about what what is the basis for רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar for
רבי אליעזר. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי אליעזר
or רבי אלעאי, Rabbi Elai, כמאן סברה, k'man savra, who does he
hold like? Of course he could have said he held like that
ברייתא, braisa but what it really means is like where does he
get the strength to פסקן like the one opinion at the end
of the משנה and to ignore the other two opinions that treat
it as a ספק. So he gets it from ריש לקיש, Resh
Lakish, who seems to take this say this for פסק הלכה. psak
halacha. Let's take a look. Here's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says:
לא אמרו טומטום ספק אלא באדם. Lo amru tumtum safek ela b'adam.
When did they say a טומטום was doubtful male or female? If
it happened by a human, which we've been ignoring, we're going to
next the next פרק perek we're going to do a revisiting of
all of this פרק perek for humans. This is all for animals.
So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said a טומטום is only a ספק
by humans, הואיל וזכרותו ונקבותו במקום אחד, ho'il v'zachruto u'nekvuto b'makom echad,
since the genitalia are basically in the same place. So you can't
tell based on where the urine is coming from, you can't tell
if it's male or female. So that it remains a ספק by
humans. אבל בבהמה, Aval b'behema, but in an animal, מטיל מים במקום
זכרות זכר, matil mayim b'makom zachrut zachar, if the urine comes out
where the male organ would be, it's a male. מטיל מים במקום
נקבה נקבה, matil mayim b'makom nekeva nekeva, and it comes out where
the female organ would be, it's a female. And we're not concerned
that the male organ is somehow bent over. So you see ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish said not just as a theoretical, but as פסק
הלכה, psak halacha, that number one, טומטום is not categorically excluded, and
number two though, even as a ספק you can you can determine
the ספק based on where the urine comes out. So therefore if
the urine comes out from where a female would urinate, it is
a definite female and it's not a בכור. All right, so that
is now our our question
on ריש לקיש Resh Lakish then, how does he or
okay, but I mean why did ריש לקיש Resh Lakish know to
פסקן that position? It's an interesting point, why was he offended that
maybe that's why they switched the gears to רבי אלעאי, Rabbi Elai,
who was a little bit less of an authoritative אמורא amora than
a ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. But you're right, I mean אמוראים amoraim
sometimes do pick the positions that make sense to them. It's a
good point, it's a good point, like why is ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish any better? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה רבי אושעיא, matkif
lah Rabbi Oshaya, רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya asked ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish,
וליחוש שמא נהפכה זכרותו לנקבותו, v'leicheish shema nehepcha zachruto l'nekvuto, what we've
been saying before, how can you פסקן with such definitiveness
that it's a female? Maybe the male organ bent is bent over
and it's coming from the rear, so or coming from where the
female would urinate? אמר ליה, כמאן, k'man, כרבי מאיר דחייש למיעוטא, k'Rabbi
Meir d'chaish l'mi-uta, who you want me to be like? You want
me to be like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that's concerned with small
possibilities? It's possible, anything is possible, but I'm going to go by
normally, normally if it's coming from the rear it means that it's
a female. Okay, don't worry me about those oh well what if
this and what if that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אביי
בר אבין ורב חנינא בר אבין דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye bar Avin v'Rav
Hanina bar Avin d'amri tarvaihu, they both said, no, you can't just
answer oh we don't פסקן like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אפילו תימא
רבנן, Afillu teima Rabbanan, even if you go like the רבנן who
normally don't aren't concerned with minor possibilities, אשתני אשתני, ishtani ishtani, since
it's different, it's different. Meaning, this whole animal is very strange in
terms of what's happening with its genitalia, it's all covered up, so
who knows what's going on behind there? You can't make any assumptions
based on אשתני, ishtani, you can't make any assumptions based on what
normally the genitalia are because the whole thing is different. So therefore
you normally you would have to be חושש choshesh here that concerned
that it came out from where the female normally urinates.
I'm sorry, so is that saying that
you have to treat it as a ספק? Okay, you can't just
say oh normally that wouldn't happen. This is not
normal. So exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא אשתני ולא אשתני
תנאי היא, leima ishtani v'lo ishtani tana'ei hi, maybe this question about
once something is different, how different do we assume it is in
this genital area, maybe that's a debate of תנאים. tana'im. And let's
take a look. Now we're going to still talk about a טומטום
but in a little different way, not about urinating but about other
questions. So let's take a look. דתניא, D'tanya, we תני ברייתא, tan
a braita, and now we're going about humans. טומטום שקידש קידושיו קידושין,
Tumtum she-kidesh kidusho kidushin, let's say a טומטום marries a woman. Okay,
now he now it's interesting by the way, you should be aware
that the גמרא does not determine male or female by secondary sex
characteristics. No, although his genitalia are still covered up, we're he's going
to be in this position of ספק זכר ספק נקבה. Okay, by
the way anyway this is true, right, with some people that have
either XXY's or different types of things, right, the secondary sex characteristics
are not always determinant anyway. So this this טומטום, we don't know
what his הלכה sex is, and he marries a woman. So it's
binding because he might be a male and therefore at least it's
a ספק קידושין. safek kidushin. נתקדש, Niskadesh, let's say how somebody marries
the טומטום, a man marries the טומטום. So also קידושין kiddushin קידושין,
kiddushin, it's binding מספק, maybe he's a female. וחולץ וחולצין
לאשתו—let's vecholeitz vecholtzin le'ishto say his brother died, he has to—he can
do חליצה chalitzah to his brother's wife because maybe he's a male.
Now, of course, if his brother's—if there's other brothers around, then they
still need to do חליצה chalitzah because maybe he's a female. Okay,
but if he's the only brother, then he has to do חליצה
chalitzah because—I mean he's the only whatever sibling, he has to do
חליצה. chalitzah. Also, let's say he dies and his wife is left
without children—obviously she doesn't have children because his genitalia is covered up.
Okay? So his wife is left without children, so then it might
have been a good קידושין kiddushin and therefore a brother of his
would have to do חליצה chalitzah as well. What? Well, we're getting
there. ומייבם לאשתו—he umiyabeim le'ishto obviously can't do יבום yibum because his
genitalia is covered up, but if he dies, a brother can do
יבום yibum to his wife. Why? ממנפשך—either miman nafshach he's a man
and it's a מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, or it was a
woman, it was never קידושין. kiddushin. So there's not a problem of
marrying your brother's wife because it was never קידושין. kiddushin. So therefore
he can do יבום yibum to his wife. Yes. Okay, so fine.
So that's the—that is this
טומטום. ותניא חדא—one Vetanya chada ברייתא. braisa ותניא אידך—we Vetanya idach have
another ברייתא. אשת טומטום, Eshes tumtum, the wife of this טומטום, חולצת
choletzes has to have חליצה chalitzah because maybe he was a
male. Okay, ולא מתייבמת—you velo misyabemes can't do יבום yibum to her.
Now, why can you not do יבום yibum to her? Why don't
we say the same point? Either it was a valid קידושין kiddushin
and he's a male, you do יבום, yibum, or it wasn't a
קידושין kiddushin at all because he was a female and fine, it's
just getting married afresh. So do you know what you can—what do
you think? What are you thinking, Charlie? Why wouldn't you be able
to do יבום? yibum?
Well, you can't—no, he died!
You're doing יבום yibum with his wife, right? Why not?
So let's figure it out. יבום yibum is only in the case
where you know that
there's זרע לאחיו, zera le'achiv, right? Right. In this case, he could
never have had זרע zera anyway.
Ah, so that's the question. In his current state, he couldn't have
זרע, zera, but maybe it will—maybe in the future it will be—it
will come—it will, you know, be uncovered and he will be able
to have זרע. zera. But he's dead! He didn't. Doesn't matter. Let's
say they—let's say they die before they ever consummated the marriage. Okay?
Let's say he was having, you know, let's say he was having
fertility problems and he was seeing a fertility specialist or whatever. Okay,
as long as it was theoretically possible, okay, then it is in
that category. So the fact that it was just covered up would
not have been enough. The question we're going to raise is: since
there's this issues with his genitalia that they're covered up, maybe we
have to be concerned that he's also סריס. saris. Okay, so that's
the question. But just the fact that he's been physically not able
until now, he might have been able in the future. So can
you do יבום yibum to his wife? Okay, so גמרא says סברוה—we
savruha assumed דהא אמר רבי עקיבא. dehacha amreih Rebbe Akiva. We're all
going like רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva דאמר סריס חמה לא חולץ ולא
מייבם. de'amar saris chamah lo choletz velo miyabeim. Somebody who is a
סריס, saris, sterile, not because actually deformed genitalia, but just because סריס
חמה saris chamah means by the sun. But it means through sort
of like, you know, not because anything is wrong with his genitalia
but just naturally sterile. Okay, so can that person who was never
able להקים זרע? lehakin zera? So therefore would there be יבום? yibum?
So we're assuming like רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that everybody says that
there's no need for חליצה chalitzah or יבום yibum in that case.
Okay, because he never was in that category of having children. The
husband, the dead husband. So מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mailav behah kamifligi?
Let's say this is the debate. דמאן דאמר חולץ וחולצין לאשתו, deman
de'amar choletz vecholtzin le'ishto, the one that says you still do חליצה
chalitzah to his wife and not only that ומייבם את אשתו, umiyabeim
es ishto, obviously is not concerned that the dead husband was a
סריס. saris. Because if the dead husband was a סריס, saris, then
he could not do יבום. yibum. Maybe he was married to her
and it would be his sister-in-law without a מצוה mitzvah of יבום,
yibum, right? Is that clear? If the brother—if he was a male
and married to her, it's a sister-in-law. The only thing that allows
יבום yibum is the מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. Okay, but that
would only be if the dead brother wasn't a
סריס. saris. And why would that be? If he's a סריס saris
there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום? yibum? Yes. Right, right.
וחולץ וחולצין לאשתו ומייבם את אשתו—לא אמרינן הוה ואשתני ואשתני.
amrinan hovai ve'ishni ve'ishni
We don't say just because his genitalia were covered up, just because
he was a טומטום means we have to be concerned of the
possibility that he's sterile. I mean, anybody could have been sterile, but
we're not concerned about it just because of—when we're not more concerned
about it here than anywhere else. ומאן דאמר חולצת ולא מתייבמת, uman
de'amar choletzes velo misyabemes, you only do חליצה, chalitzah, not יבום, yibum,
אמרינן הוה ואשתני ואשתני—we're concerned he was a סריס. saris. Now, because
he might not have been a סריס, saris, you have to do
חליצה, chalitzah, right? Maybe the dead brother wasn't a סריס. saris. But
because we are concerned here more than normal that he was a
סריס, saris, then you're not allowed to do יבום. yibum. Okay, so
there you see that once we're concerned about one thing with this
טומטום, I mean, once it's, you know, once it's different, we're concerned
about other issues related to his genitalia as well. So the גמרא
says לא. No, that's not the debate. דכולי עלמא אמרינן הוה ואשתני
ואשתני—everybody dechulei alma amrinan hovai ve'ishni ve'ishni could say that we are
concerned that things are different. So then why do we debate whether
you can do יבום? yibum? Then you shouldn't be allowed to do
יבום, yibum, maybe he was
a
סריס. saris. הרי... harei... So the one that says you do ייבום
yibbum says you could do ייבום yibbum even if you were sterile,
and the one that says you don't do ייבום yibbum says no,
I פוסק posek like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you don't do
it if he was sterile, and since he might have been sterile,
you're not allowed to do ייבום. yibbum. Okay, ומאן תנא אליבא דרבי
עקיבא? u'man tanna aliba de'Rabbi Akiva? And who is this תנא tanna
now according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that is saying that he
might be sterile and therefore you don't do ייבום? yibbum? אילימא רבי
יהודה, Ilima Rabbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, הוי ודאי
סריס משוי ליה. havai vadai sris mashvi lei. We know that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would consider a טומטום to be a definite סריס.
sris. And therefore, if that were true, you wouldn't even do חליצה.
chalitzah. You would say since he's a טומטום, he was definitely sterile
and therefore there's not even חליצה chalitzah done to his wife, right?
You understand that when you do חליצה chalitzah not ייבום, yibbum, that's
what you do in a case of a ספק. Since right, you
can't do ייבום yibbum because it might be your sister-in-law without a
מצווה mitzvah of ייבום, yibbum, but you do חליצה chalitzah because if
there were a מצווה mitzvah of ייבום yibbum you have to free
the woman through חליצה. chalitzah. So our thing, our one ברייתא that
said you do חליצה chalitzah not ייבום, yibbum, which means he's a
doubtful סריס. sris. The other one said no, you can even do
ייבום. yibbum. So according to one, we don't assume he's sterile, we
don't treat him differently, we don't say since one thing is different,
something else is different. The other one said no, since he was
a טומטום we're concerned that he was sterile and therefore חליצה chalitzah
no ייבום. yibbum. But now we're going to say who says that
position? Because there's a position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that goes
even one step further, says that he's a definitely sterile, that we
assume he's definitely sterile and you don't even do חליצה. chalitzah. Where
is... because he's a... because he's a סריס בידי שמים
sris bidei
shamayim
and we assume it definitely, right. So how does we know... how
do we know that? דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, רבי
יהודה אומר טומטום שנקרע ונמצא זכר הרי זה לא יחלוץ מפני שהוא
כסריס. Rabbi Yehuda omer tumtum shenikra venimtza zachar harei zeh lo yachalotz
mipnei shehu kesris. And there you have it. A טומטום it was
torn, the covering skin, and it turns out he was male, הרי
זה לא יחלוץ מפני שהוא כסריס. harei zeh lo yachalotz mipnei shehu
kesris.
Don't do חליצה chalitzah on his brother's wife. Now it's his brother's
the one that's dead. He can't do חליצה chalitzah for his brother's
wife because he's a סריס sris and therefore his חליצה chalitzah will
not free this woman. But he didn't say ספק סריס. safek sris.
He says הרי זה כשהוא כסריס, harei zeh keshehu kesris, which the
גמרא assumes to mean means that he is a definite סריס. sris.
כסריס. Kesris. I know. I know, but that's how the גמרא interprets
it. Now because the same thing is true, since you can't do
the מצווה mitzvah of ייבום, yibbum, if he's sterile he can't do
חליצה chalitzah to free the woman and another sibling would have to
do the מצווה. mitzvah. But you're right, you could have read it
ספק, but the גמרא is reading it as ודאי. vadai.
And he wouldn't do חליצה chalitzah to his wife either, right?
Exactly. Therefore our משנה would not have... our ברייתא would not have
been רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אלא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה היא. Ela
Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda hi. It's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yossi
berabbi Yehuda. דתניא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר טומטום לא חולץ שמא
יקרע וימצא סריס חמה. Detanya Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda omer tumtum lo
choletz shema yikara veyimatza sris chamah.
Maybe it'll be torn and it'll turn out that he will be
a... that he will be
sterile. Now...
אטו כל דמיקרע זכר משתכח
נקבה לא משתכח?
Atu kol
demikara
zachar mishtakach nekeivah lo mishtakach? What do you mean maybe it'll be
sterile? There's another reason not to do חליצה. chalitzah. Maybe he's a
woman! So the גמרא says okay, שמא קאמר. shema ka'amar. You're right,
שמא. shema. שמא יקרע וימצא נקבה. Shema yikara veyimatza nekeivah. Maybe it'll
turn out he'll be a woman. אי נמי זכר, Ei nami zachar,
and even if he's a male, this is the guy that's alive,
his brother is dead, נמי שמא ימצא סריס חמה, nami shema yimatza
sris chamah,
maybe he'll be sterile. So you see here that there's one opinion
that assumes that a... that a טומטום is a סריס, sris, that's
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The other says no, even if he might
be a סריס. sris. But might be a סריס, sris, so he
still shouldn't do חליצה chalitzah to the wife because maybe he's a
סריס sris and he won't free the woman, the... you know, the
widow, and another brother has to do it. Okay, so just...
it's incidental by the way that you haven't had children, maybe he's
a סריס.
sris. Right, right, which is funny, you wonder why they haven't had
children yet. Maybe... what? Or maybe it's the woman. So that is
absolutely correct, which is why you have רבי אליעזר's position, which is
that even if it's a סריס sris you still do חליצה chalitzah
and ייבום yibbum because of that. But by the way, this is
the... this is the living brother, but it's the sort of same
logic that's being applied. But yeah, that's the funny thing, that just
because they've been living together for ten years and haven't had kids,
we don't say maybe the husband was a סריס. sris. And we're
only worried about it if we see something physically different. But you're
right, like normally you would be חושש choshesh for it in general,
yes.
Can a sterile person marry? Yes.
Yes. If there is a case about sort of פצוע דכא, ptzua
daka, certain types of... of... injured genitalia, not just sterile, then you're
not allowed, but then we define that category very narrowly. Okay, but
that's a separate discussion. But just sterile, absolutely. There's questions in the
תורה about like, you know, crushed testicles and... and... you know, other
types of things, which cannot, but again we define those in very...
is that person the מצווה mitzvah to... to reproduce is only on
the... is it only on the male? Because you're preventing a woman
from having...
Yeah, so that... that is true. You know, although nowadays there are
other ways. But yeah, the woman could have had children from another
man also, could have been a second marriage for her. But anyway,
but the... but your answer is correct on both counts. Yes, can
marry and yes, we פוסקן, posken, although it's debated, we פוסקן posken
that the מצווה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru u'rvu is on the
male.
No, but my question is also like let's say if יקרע ונמצא
נקבה, yikara venimtza nekeivah, would we say she'd also be
an
אילונית?
ailonit? No no, we weren't talking about doing יבום yibum on her.
That was that was but I'm saying fine, but that wasn't discussed
at all here.
No no, I'm asking.
Okay, I don't know. Okay, fine. Moving on. Anyway, so the גמרא
says, okay, so now we have so now we have right three
possibilities about this man that's a טומטום and חליצה chalitza and יבום.
yibum. One is that oh is that if it turns out that
he's a man or the possibility he's a man we don't assume
anything else is different, we assume he's not he's you know just
as unlikely to be sterile as any other man. And therefore you
do everything, חליצה, chalitza, יבום, yibum, etc., you don't have to be
concerned about anything if he dies with his wife etc. You just
have to be concerned that you don't know male or female if
it's still covered up. Then you have the other possibility is that
even if it turns out he's a man, we have to be
concerned specially here that it's he's sterile. So you don't do יבום
yibum to his wife. Or רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda goes even further
and says we assume he's definitely sterile. And now the גמרא is
just going to wrap it up by saying what's the נפקא מינה.
nafka mina. מאי בינייהו mai beinayhu what do I care whether he's
definitely sterile or only possibly sterile? So אמר רבא Amar Rava ליפסול
במקום אחים. lifsol b'makom achim. Number one is to if there are
other siblings with the following נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Okay, if one
brother does חליצה, chalitza, once one thing is done with this woman
the other brothers cannot say oh I wanted to do יבום. yibum.
They could say it but it won't help them. They're not allowed
to do יבום yibum once חליצה chalitza is done. So if this
טומטום goes ahead and does חליצה chalitza to this his brother's wife,
then if you say he was definitely sterile then you could say
the חליצה chalitza was meaningless and I'm another brother and I want
to do יבום. yibum. Okay, or you could flip it the other
way it was meaningless and she still requires חליצה chalitza to be
free either way. But that was completely meaningless. If you say he
might he only might have been sterile he might not, right? Then
it was possibly a good חליצה. chalitza. So therefore I should still
do another חליצה chalitza to help her out because she's not hasn't
had a definite חליצה chalitza done but I certainly can't do יבום
yibum because she might have already had a חליצה chalitza done to
her. So that חליצה chalitza because it's possibly good prevents me from
doing יבום. yibum. That's one נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
Wait, so either way he still can't do יבום, yibum,
right? Is
that what you just said? Yes. No, if he was definitely sterile
then I can do יבום. yibum. He was definitely sterile, it was
a complete non-חליצה chalitza so it meant nothing. This טומטום did חליצה,
chalitza, so if you say he's definitely sterile if he's male then
it meant absolutely nothing and I can do יבום. yibum. If he's
only ספק sterile then it might have been good and
therefore I can't do יבום yibum to
begin with really if there are other brothers. Right. And that's the
other נפקא מינה nafka mina ולחלוץ שלא במקום אחים איכא בינייהו. v'lachlotz
shelo b'makom achim ika beinayhu. Let's say there are no other brothers.
So if he's definitely sterile and there's no other brothers, she doesn't
need any חליצה, chalitza, she's totally free. But if he's only possibly
sterile and there's no other brothers, she still would require a חליצה
chalitza from him because he might be because if he's not sterile
then then he
then he has a מצוה mitzvah of חליצה chalitza or יבום yibum
and she would still require that חליצה. chalitza. So הדרן עלך אילם.
Hadran alach Eilem. יישר כח, yasher koach, that was a major accomplishment.
And you know and I do think that the again the really
fascinating the range of possibilities we've seen about טומטום and אנדרוגינוס just
to again repeat them. אנדרוגינוס is the same for all, like it's
not it's not case specific. There are three possibilities. One is that
it's intrinsically indeterminate male female. It has a definition of ספק. It's
not like you're going to determine one case is one and one
is the other. The category is indeterminate but we only acknowledge two
genders. The other possibility is male with a with something
with a מום, right again not considering the alternative of female with
a מום. So male with a מום. And the third possibility is
that there's a third gender. By טומטום, it's a little more interesting.
By טומטום there's you know there's the possibility that that we ignore
that we reject the possibility of a third gender. And then there's
the possibility of רבי יוחנן that no, the טומטום also at least
is a third category. It's an excluded category הלכתית. halachically. Maybe it's
not actually a third gender but at least הלכתית halachically it's excluded
from the world of קרבנות. And then the other possibility which says
tries to if you would like more normalize it and say that
no no no, it's a ספק זכר ונקבה safek zachar u'nekeivah and
maybe we can even determine whether it's a female or male based
on where it urinates from or maybe we can't determine because הוא
דאשתי והיא דאשתי. hu d'ashti v'hi d'ashti. So whole so just let
me just finish. So whole range of possibilities about you know טומטום
and אנדרוגינוס and we will also we will get to revisit a
lot of these things when we turn to the next פרק perek
for מומין. mumin. Look forward to seeing you then.